Amos E. Dolbear Papers MS016
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Amos E. Dolbear Papers
1877 -- 1910
1872 -- 1969
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Dolbear, Amos Emerson
MS016
15.75 Linear Feet
12 Volumes
1 Artifact(s)
Arrangement
This collection is organized into five series: Letters, publications, and writings; Telephone prototypes, models, and inventions; The Telephone Appeals and patent related documents; Photographs; and Personal and family papers.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes letters, publications, writings, personal papers, a commemorative Ballou Hall plaque, photographs, notebooks, and apparatus connected with Dolbear's academic work and with experiments regarding the invention of the telephone.
Biographical / Historical
Amos Emerson Dolbear (1837-1910) was born in Norwich, Connecticut on November 10, 1837. Following his father's death, he and his mother moved to Newport, Rhode Island, where he remained with his mother until her death in 1847. He then went to live on a relative's farm in New Hampshire and eventually was sent to Worcester, Massachusetts, to learn a trade. He was employed briefly at a pistol-making factory. At the age of eighteen, he headed west, finding employment as a school teacher in Missouri. Suffering from poor health, he soon returned to New England and continued to carry out physically strenuous jobs in Rhode Island and Massachusetts.
Desiring a better education in order to advance professionally, Dolbear enrolled in Ohio Wesleyan University. As a result of his outstanding performance, he soon became an assistant in both the Physics and Chemistry Departments. He graduated in 1866 following two years of study and became an assistant instructor in the Chemistry Department the University of Michigan. He received two degrees, an MA and a ME, from Michigan. Dolbear then assumed the position of assistant professor of Natural History at Kentucky University. After two years he moved on to become professor of Physics and Chemistry at Bethany College in 1868. In 1869, he married Alice Hood, with whom he had six children. Before leaving West Virginia, he served as the mayor of Bethany from 1871-1872.
In 1874, Dolbear arrived at Tufts College, accepting the chair of the Physics and Astronomy Department and continued to pursue his interest of the study of the convertibility of sound into electricity. He stayed at the college for the remainder of his academic career.
Dolbear contributed many notable inventions to the scientific world, including the static telephone, the electric gyroscope used to demonstrate the Earth's rotation, the opeidoscope, and a new system of incandescent lighting. In 1876, Dolbear patented a magneto electric telephone, in 1879 a static telephone, and three years later he managed to communicate over a distance of a quarter of a mile without wires in the Earth and obtained a patent on the wireless telegraph before Hertz or Guglielmo Marconi. His research on the static telephone was conducted in his laboratory on the top floor of Ballou Hall, and the first transmissions using the device were made from Ballou Hall to his house on Professors Row. In 1876, Dolbear patented a magneto electric telephone, in 1879 a static telephone, and three years later he managed to communicate over a distance of a quarter of a mile without wires in the Earth. It is interesting to note that the Tufts professor was ahead of Hertz and Marconi. He received a U.S. patent for a wireless telegraph in March of that year.
Dolbear was a member of the American Association of Arts and Sciences, the American Association for the Advancement of Science and worked as an examiner at the World's Fair. He was recognized for his contributions to science at both the Paris Exposition in 1881 and the Crystal Palace Exposition in 1882. He published several books, articles, and pamphlets, including "The Art of Projecting" (1876), "The Speaking Telephone" (1877), "Sound and its Phenomena" (1885), "First Principles of Natural Philosophy" (1897), "Modes of Motion" (1897) and "Matter, Ether, Motion."
Dolbear was one of only three faculty members to offer unqualified support to the College's decision to admit women beginning in 1892. In 1905-6, he became the first faculty member to be granted permission for a full academic year's leave with pay prior to the establishment of a sabbatical leave program at Tufts in 1908. Dolbear died on February 23, 1910 following a long illness.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Dolbear, Amos Emerson; Telephone -- History; Faculty papers
- Lectures, publications, and writings, 1872 -- 1910; MS016.001; 4.85 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains materials related to Amos E. Dolbear's lectures and publications on a wide range of scientific and social science topics. The bulk of the material within this series are drafts of articles written for publication. The drafts are contained within numerous notebooks.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged as found.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Notebook # 1 Bacon vs. Shakespeare; Report to Brodbury Stover Storage Battery Co; Cosmopolitan: Telegraphing without wires; Electromagnetic waves; Electrical exhibit at World's Fair, 1893 -- 1898; MS016.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 2 The Dynamo, MS016.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 3 Emerson's thoughts on science, MS016.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 4 Energy, MS016.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 5 Ether waves, Radiation or light, Phosphor and fluorescence, The year's work in physics, Spectroscopic phenomena, MS016.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 6 Ether waves, MS016.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 7 Ether waves, MS016.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 8 Heat, MS016.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 9 Heat, MS016.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 10 How phenomena are interpreted, Old and new provisions for science, MS016.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 11 Matter and its properties, The ether, On motion, Energy, MS016.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 12 Molecular physics, Matter and its qualities, The kind of universe we live in, MS016.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 13 First principles of natural philosophy, MS016.001.001.00013 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 14 Objects of all science (lecture at Woods Hole, 1897); Electrical phenomena or how electricity acts, MS016.001.001.00014 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 15 Pedagogy as an art and as a science, Old and new theories of education, MS016.001.001.00015 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 16 Pedagogy and an art and as a science, MS016.001.001.00016 (Box 1)
    This folder contains both handwritten and typed copies of this article.
  - Notebook # 17 Physical fields, MS016.001.001.00017 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 18 Physics VI, MS016.001.001.00018 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 19 The relations of physics to physiology, MS016.001.001.00019 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 20 The scientific bequest of the 19th to the 20th century, Bequest of the 19th to the 20th century, 1900; MS016.001.001.00020 (Box 1)
    This folder contains both handwritten and typed copies of "Bequest of the 19th to the 20th Century."
  - Notebook # 21 The problems of the 20th century, Electricity's future, MS016.001.001.00021 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 22 Sound, MS016.001.001.00022 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 23 Sound, MS016.001.001.00023 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 24 Sound, MS016.001.001.00024 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 25 Relations of physics to ethics, Utopia, MS016.001.001.00025 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 26 What went ye out for to see! (Woods Hole lecture, July 1896); What matter can do depends upon what motion it has; Organization, MS016.001.001.00026 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 27 On electricty and its phenomena, MS016.001.001.00027 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 28 Electricity and magnetism, MS016.001.001.00028 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 29 Electricity, Chemism, MS016.001.001.00029 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 30 On electricty as a form of energy, 1882; MS016.001.001.00030 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 31 Electricity and Civilization, MS016.001.001.00031 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 32 Electricity, MS016.001.001.00032 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 33 On electricity, MS016.001.001.00033 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 34 On electrical terminology, Electrical instruments for measurement, MS016.001.001.00034 (Box 1)
    The notebook in this folder also contains information on galvanometers, tangent galvanometer, reflecting galvanometer, astatic galvonometer, resistance coils, standard cells, conductors, keys, experimental work, galvanometer reduction factor, resistance, resistance of batteries, Wheatsone bridge, primary batteries and their reactions, secondary batteries, and the relation of electromotive force to chemical reaction.
  - Notebook # 35 Induction coils for commercial work (Cosmopolitan, Jan. 1895); Electricity in disinfection (Cosmopolitan, 1896); Electrical action upon living things in water (Cosmopolitan, Feb. 1896); Preface to Growth of Physical Knowledge; Preface to nat. philosophy; Science and pedagogical science (given in Boston, April 30, 1898); Reasons for Sunday observance (Free Religions Association, May 5, 1898), 1895 -- 1898; MS016.001.001.00035 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 36 On lightning; Vacuum tubes and Electric lighting (written for Cosmopolitan, May 5, 1896); What chemistry can do for mankind; The modern alchemist; antiquity of the Earth, MS016.001.001.00036 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 37 Mechanism and life; On lightning; Eureka!; Galilio [Galileo], a physician; Newton; Franklin; Faraday; Joule, MS016.001.001.00037 (Box 1)
  - Notebook # 38 The phenomena of electricity (given Feb. 20, 1888); On nature of electricity (April 1888); On the growth of sciences, MS016.001.001.00038 (Box 1)
  - On telephone systems - lecture delivered at Franklin Institute, December 11, 1885, MS016.001.001.00039 (Box 1)
  - Writings A-C, 1892; MS016.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
    This folder contains a typewritten bibliography of Dolbear's published works, which may not be complete. It also includes scientific articles written by and in response to Dolbear, a handwritten address given by Dolbear at Tremont Temple on May 27, 1892, and an address to teachers in Cheshire County, N.H. Marlboro. There is an essay on atomic vibration and maximum temperature,along with an essay concerning Dolbear's inventions and experiments in electricity, telegraphy, and telephony - both of which are written in Dolbear's hand.
    Telegraph; Telephone; Dolbear, Amos Emerson
  - Writings D-E, 1893; MS016.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
    This folder contains handwritten, typewritten, and printed essays by Dolbear on a number of topics, including the direction of an electric current; disappointing results of teaching science (1893); the educational method in the light of evolution; and many topical essays related to electricity, from electricity and civilization to electricity as a weed killer and electric photography.
    Electricity
  - Writings E, MS016.001.002.00003 (Box 2)
    This folder contains handwritten, typed, and printed essays on a number of electricity-related topics, electro-magnetism, and ether. Also included are essays on evolution and education; Emerson's thoughts on science, according to Dolbear; and a number of handwritten prompting notes. The copyright certificate for Dolbear's "Elements of Physics" is also included.
  - Writings F-L, MS016.001.002.00004 (Box 2)
    Dolbear's varied interests are represented by the writings in this folder. Articles about Moses Farmer, principles of social reform, the food supply in the future, the future of electricity, incandescent and fluorescent light, and life from a physical standpoint are included. Essays are handwritten, typed, or in printed forms.
  - Writings M-N, MS016.001.002.00005 (Box 2)
    This folder contains Dolbear's writings on the topics of magnetism, matter, machinery, medication by electric osmosis, education, electricity, apparatus for demonstration the motion of the earth, nerves and knowledge, galvanometers, geometry, sun spots, astronomy and the portelectric system (electrical transportation).
  - Writings O, 1888; MS016.001.002.00006 (Box 2)
    This folder contains works on a number of Dolbear's interests, including the importance of a knowledge of science (1888), introduction of physics to grammar school maximum temperatures, matter as energy, opinions, organization of atoms and molecules, vibrations and pitch, contact theory of electricity, physical nomenclature, and the appeal of food.
  - Writings O, MS016.001.002.00007 (Box 2)
    Dolbear's writings included in this folder cover the following topics: odds against uneducated inventors, importance of knowing your ancestors, chemismor chemical affinity and chemical attraction, electricity, electromagnets, gravity, immortality from the physical standpoint, high school science teaching.
  - Writings P-R, MS016.001.002.00008 (Box 2)
    Dolbear's writings on a number of topics, including a plan for electrical model of electric phenomena, philosophy of education, phenomena of vortex ringe, pedagogical physics, paracelsus, pioneer of science, relation of physics to ethics, religious life in colleges.
  - Writings S-Z, 1891 -- 1906; MS016.001.002.00009 (Box 2)
    Included in this folder are a number of Dolbear's writings on a variety of subjects, including a scheme for railroad signaling, the science and pedagogy of science (given at School Masters Club, 1898), science in schools, science in the 19th century, science and theism, science problems of the twentieth century, scientific bequest of the 19th to the twentieth century, may 1900 (duplicates article from June 7, 1900 with "unity" header removed), street dangers and unsightliness (1891), slate writing-psychic/medium powers (transcript which reveals Dolbear's brother was killed at Gettysburg), solving the mystery of life in the laboratory, the spectral well of Virginia (1893), strong ad week points in high school education, Sunday observance, teachers in the Ozarks (1906), telegraphing without wires, theism and ethics, science in schools (1893), thirty years ago at Ohio Weslyan (1895), viewing electromagnetic waves, truancy, truth, utopia, vacuum tube electric lamps (1896), Wilhelm Eduard Weber (1892), what can be done with a sunbeam (1901), will man ever fly (1894), wireless telegraph and the ether (1903), and wireless telegraphy and how it works (1902).
  - Untitled manuscripts and notes, MS016.001.002.00010 (Box 2)
  - Telephone-related writings, MS016.001.002.00011 (Box 2)
  - Spiritualism, MS016.001.002.00012 (Box 2)
  - General tables for the qualitative analysis of common inorganic substances, 1872; MS016.001.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - International Electrical exhibition: report of examiners of sections XIV-XVI batteries, 1884; MS016.001.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - International Electrical exhibition: report of examiners of sections XXIX "educational apparatus", 1884; MS016.001.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - Matter, Ether, Motion clippings, 1892 -- 1893; MS016.001.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - Mechanical conceptions of electrical phenomena, 1896; MS016.001.003.00005 (Box 3)
  - On the development of the new telephonic system, 1882; MS016.001.003.00006 (Box 3)
  - On the organization of atoms and molecules, 1888 -- 1889; MS016.001.003.00007 (Box 3)
  - Thomson's process of electric welding report on state of the art and process by A. E. Dolbear, MS016.001.003.00008 (Box 3)
  - Clippings of articles on various subjects, MS016.001.004.00001 (Box 4)
    This is a bound scrapbook pf newspaper and journal clippings assembled by Dolbear. Although a number of the clippings relate to the telephone, several other topics on which Dolbear wrote.
    Scrapbook; Telephone; Dolbear, Amos Emerson
  - Oversize Documents, MS016.001.005.001 (Box Large Map Case 2 Drawer 7)
    Documents in this box include writings, blue prints, and legal documents from series one Blueprint for transmitter box, drawn by H.C. Buck copy of provisional specification of Amos Emerson Dolbear -an improved method or means for providing ground or earth connections for electrical circuits, March 1882, London Privy Council, Uk, in the matter of the petition for prolongation of term of Dolbear's patent, this patent specifies that air insulation be used to insure low capacity insulation primarily rather than good insulation and therefore better transmission. It is the first patent and the forerunner of all modern paper and air insulated telephone cable, copy of provisional specification of Amos Emerson Dolbear improvements in electrical cables, 1882, London plans for 4 large transmitter boxes of solid mahogany, drawn by H. C. buck growth of science nerves and knowledge old and new educational methods in the light of evolution science mechanical conceptions of electrical phenomena Dolbear's prolongation, 1896 copy of A.E. Dolbear esq to Jose D. Husbands, Esq Assignment of rights for use of Dolbear's inventions and improvements in Chile, Peru, Ecuador, and Bolivia, 1882 Dolbear set full size plans, 1882
    Dolbear, Amos Emerson
  - Clippings, 1874 -- 1910; MS016.001.007.00006 (Box MS016 Shared 1)
  - Matter, Ether and Motion, 1894; MS016.001.008.00001; Dolbear, Amos E. (Box 8)
  - "Amos Emerson Dolbear": a biography by Inza S. Dolbear (to p. 121), MS016.001.011.00046 (Box 11)
  - "Amos Emerson Dolbear": a biography by Inza S. Dolbear (p.122 to end), MS016.001.011.00047 (Box 11)
- Telephone prototypes, models, and inventions, 1880 -- 1893; MS016.002; 10.15 Linear Feet
  This series contains telephone prototypes, models, and other Dolbear inventions
  Identification of prototypes and models in this series has been made by comparing the donor gift agreement, exhibit placards, and, in some cases, tags attached to the artifact. No direct comparison has been made between the objects and plans, designs, or patent documents found elsewhere in the collection.
  Missing from this series is a model wall phone for demonstration at World's Fair bearing label "Dolbear Electric Telephone Co. The unit had a static generator and ringing generator (the latter using horseshoe magnets) and includes two bells and a switch shutting off the circuit when receiver is hung up.
  Also missing is an enclosed rotophone, a double coil permanent magnet receiver with diaphragm between two magnets, and two receivers or transmitters.
  Also included is one telephone prototype and components retrieved from the attic of Robinson Hall (Physics Department) before the building's renovation in 2015. It is unclear whether the components were disassembled from a single prototype, or include spare parts from other projects. This accession is housed in three boxes: 034, 035, and 036.
  - Early experimental form of magnetic telephone. Consists of two small horeshoe magnets mounted on board containing diaphragm and coil., MS016.002.006.00005 (Box 6)
    Magnets are no longer attached.
    Telephone; Dolbear, Amos Emerson
  - Hollow block microphone using parchment diaphragm - an early experimental approach, MS016.002.006.00008 (Box 6)
  - Hollow experimental microphone in box (rather than block) shape with metal diaphragm, MS016.002.006.00010 (Box 6)
  - Model pole changer for telephone bells, 1885-03-03; MS016.002.006.00011 (Box 6)
  - Experimental device showing when line in use or clear. (Not a Dolbear development but used by him.), 1882; MS016.002.006.00012 (Box 6)
    This artifact is in several parts, as the case was removed to show inner workings. It was produced by Gary Telephone Signal of Boston, MA. The patent date, listed on the front emblem, is October 10, 1882.
  - Early microphone combining voice and telegraphic key., MS016.002.006.00013 (Box 6)
  - Early moving coil transmitter - receiver showing primitive coil wrapping and diaphragm held in place with wax, MS016.002.006.00015 (Box 6)
  - Combination induction coil and receiver, MS016.002.006.00016 (Box 6)
    This object is also identified as "Transmitter with double winding ratio 10-1, approximately."
  - Static telephone mounted in box for hanging or placing on flat surface combines receiver and transmitter; made for patent application, 1881-04-05; MS016.002.007.00004 (Box 7)
    This telephone duplicates patent office model for Patent #238,742, April 5, 1881
    Telephone; Artifacts (object genre); Dolbear, Amos Emerson
  - Early magnetic telephone with separate horn and three horseshoe magnets, MS016.002.008.00003 (Box 8)
    This prototype includes a detachable metal cone-shaped "horn."
  - Experimental static telephone with two terminals and adjusting screw on back, 1880; MS016.002.009.00018 (Box 9)
  - Static receiver with knob for holding in hand and adjusting screw, MS016.002.009.00024 (Box 9)
  - Receiver or transmitter, MS016.002.009.00028 (Box 9)
  - Receiver or transmitter, MS016.002.009.00029 (Box 9)
  - Receiver or transmitter, MS016.002.009.00030 (Box 9)
  - Receiver or transmitter with cord attached, MS016.002.009.00031 (Box 9)
  - Receiver or transmitter with crank handle and cord attached, MS016.002.009.00033 (Box 9)
  - Double coil permanent magnet receiver, MS016.002.009.00034 (Box 9)
  - Small variation of microphone box without bell using rectangular sounding metal for diaphragm, MS016.002.010.00007 (Box 10)
  - Experimental multiple button transmitter: up to four parties recieve message, MS016.002.010.00009 (Box 10)
  - Early dynamic receiver - transmitter with two horseshoe magnets, MS016.002.010.00014 (Box 10)
  - Experimental transmitter frame of wood, probably abandoned as non-productive after being machined., MS016.002.010.00017 (Box 10)
  - Round experimental transmitter using built-in horseshoe magnet, MS016.002.010.00019 (Box 10)
  - Experimental static receiver with sheet celluloid seperator between diaphragms, MS016.002.010.00020 (Box 10)
  - Double pole receiver in elongated egg shape, MS016.002.010.00022 (Box 10)
    This object has cloth-covered cords attached
  - Double pole receiver in hard rubber case, MS016.002.010.00023 (Box 10)
  - Heavy-duty carbon granule transmitter, MS016.002.010.00025 (Box 10)
  - Another variation of reciever with knob of hard rubber: used with transmitter box, MS016.002.010.00026 (Box 10)
  - Receiver or transmitter, MS016.002.010.00032 (Box 10)
  - Rotophone development model, 1893; MS016.002.014.00002 (Box 14)
    This rotophone was exhibited at the Chicago World's Fair of 1893
  - Transmitter box for static telephone with single bell and push button, MS016.002.015.00006 (Box 15)
  - Prototype in two pieces, MS016.002.033.00015 (Box 33)
    Donated by Mrs. Ernest G. Lorenzen, granddaughter of Amos Dolbear, August 2005.
  - Prototype and components (1 of 3), MS016.002.034 (Box 34)
    Telephone prototype and components retrieved from the attic of Robinson Hall (Physics Department) before the building's renovation in 2015. It is unclear whether the components were disassembled from a single prototype, or include spare parts from other projects. This accession is housed in three boxes: 034, 035, and 036.
  - Prototype and components (2 of 3), MS016.002.035 (Box 35)
  - Prototype and components (3 of 3), MS016.002.036 (Box 36)
- The Telephone Appeals and patent related documents, 1877 -- 1894; MS016.003; 2.45 Linear Feet; 12 Volumes
  This series contains documents related to the Telephone appeals and patent-related documents.
  - Affidavits and patents, MS016.003.011.00001 (Box 11)
  - Circuit Court of the United States: American Bell Telephone Company v. Amos E. Dolbear et al.: Affidavits in reply on motion for preliminary injuction, 1882; MS016.003.011.00002 (Box 11)
  - Circuit Court of the United States: American Bell Telephone Company v. Amos E. Dolbear et al.: Bill of Complaint, 1881; MS016.003.011.00003 (Box 11)